<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Drools | Matt Dugan]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattdugan.github.io/blog/categories/drools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattdugan.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-15T08:47:56-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattdugan.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Dugan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CamelOne 2013: Drools with Apache Camel.. Rules]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattdugan.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/camelone-2013-drools-with-apache-camel-dot-rules/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-17T14:32:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattdugan.github.io/blog/2013/06/17/camelone-2013-drools-with-apache-camel-dot-rules</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ah, the end of day Keynote, time to sit back and relax and
enjoy some light presentation that doesn&rsquo;t require any
brain power at all.</p>

<p>&hellip; But it wasn&rsquo;t meant to be.  Mark Proctor was the presenter
and when they guy talking to you looks like he can juggle
a couple of Voltswagens, you had better listen.</p>

<h2>jBPM, Drools, BRMS, what?</h2>

<p>Coming from a background heavy in BPM, the confusion is
natural and isn&rsquo;t exclusive to the decision maker, the
implementer, or even the business user.  Each technology
has certain merits and this session helped to clarify
<a href="https://www.jboss.org/drools/">Drools</a>. Drools is not so
much a &ldquo;Business Rule&rdquo; engine as it is a <em>Hybrid Reasoning
Engine</em> supporting filters, logic, and chains.  Drools
includes features for CEP (Complex Event Processing),
Decision Tables for processing high numbers of rules and
<em>Time Windowing</em> &ndash; a powerful feature allowing you to
write logic for events that occur &ldquo;over the last 5 minutes&rdquo;
or other relative time periods.</p>

<p>Next, we looked at BRMS, which packages Drools and jBPM
together along with a rule repository to achieve a very
useful integration pattern.  Often, business users struggle
with expressing a complete process (as opposed to merely
a high-level process) in BPMN.  Eventually, the implementation
starts to look like code, graphical or not.  Rules, on
the other hand, <em>are</em> code but do not easily work upward
to describe an overall business process.  Putting the
two together is a peanut-butter-on-chocolate approach
designed to achieve common code patterns using Rule
logic while expressing the transitions between rule chains
and processes using BPMN.  This concept works surprisingly
well and I have to commend the RedHat BRMS team for
thinking outside of the single-purpose tool package we see
from other vendors.</p>

<p>The upcoming release of BRMS embedding Drools 6 gains
the ability of JBoss Truth Management to enable handling
of contraditions in the rule chain &ndash; for example a
discount rule of 10% and a temporary discount of 20% are
in conflict unless the contradiction can be managed to say
that the 20% rate is valid over a particular time window
and otherwise default to the 10% rule.  MultiCore processing
additions in Drools 6 should provide a significant speedup
in the next release of BRMS as well.</p>

<p>The Drools 6 UI gets a much needed refresh to fix some
old nuances and adds resizable panels for getting work
done within the browser viewport.  The new UI is brought
together with Errai <em>(see earlier post)</em>.  Rule storage
now has a GIT backend so rule authors can take advantage
of the GIT workflow for publishing rules.  Finally, work
has been performed to create a high availability scenario
for the rules engine and everything is built together
with maven.  Drools 6 introduces a new principal object
extension point, KIE, for &ldquo;Knowledge is Everything&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Mark closed out the presentation with a brief note on
applying rules to situations you may not have thought of
as a convenient answer.  Watch Mark write Pong, implemented
in Drools.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Omj4PR3v-nI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Omj4PR3v-nI</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
