<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Just a blog.</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/events.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2013-08-30T14:30:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Atlanta JBUG: JBoss A-MQ is the hotness</title><link href="/posts/2013/Aug/30/atl-jbug-jboss-amq-is-the-hotness" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-30T14:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matt Dugan</name></author><id>tag:,2013-08-30:posts/2013/Aug/30/atl-jbug-jboss-amq-is-the-hotness</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just before Labor Day weekend, Hiram Chirino came down to our Atlanta JBoss Users Group.  We had a large local turnout interested to know more about JBoss A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; and the features coming from Apache Active &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; upstream.  An accomplished engineer, Hiram is employed by Red Hat but is also an Apache member and ActiveMQ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PMC&lt;/span&gt; chair.  Between committing to Apache ActiveMQ, Camel, Karaf, ServiceMix, Felix and Aries, Hiram leads the development of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;STOMP&lt;/span&gt; 1.1 specification.  All those things in mind, it was our pleasure at Shadow-Soft to continue our tradition of hosting the recurring Atlanta &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JBUG&lt;/span&gt; meetup with a presenter that knows what he is talking&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Messaging Oriented&amp;nbsp;Middleware&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JBoss A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; is an example of Messaging oriented Middleware (or MoM), which
essentially means that JBoss A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; offers messaging APIs and facilities to
deliver messages between message producers and message consumers in a variety
of ways.  Hiram began by describing components in messaging, such as producers,
consumers, topics, queues, destinations and selectors.  Using nicely animated
slides to visually represent message delivery, Hiram conveyed the principle
concepts of messaging that represent the baseline of functionality achieved by
A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; prior to providing additional best in class level&amp;nbsp;features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One differentiating factor of A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; is that it works hard to make messaging a
commodity between different implementation languages, physical architectures
and runtime environments.  For example, A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; supports multiple messaging
protocols (itself converting to and from OpenWire internally) appropriate to a
variety of use cases.  As well, A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; can be deployed embedded in another
application, to a Web application server, to a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JEE&lt;/span&gt; server, standalone or within
a highly available message broker cluster.  The deployment flexibility,
interoperability and multi-protocol support of A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; make it an ideal solution
for supporting Smart Grids of large numbers of embedded and mobile&amp;nbsp;devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Even More&amp;nbsp;Features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, differentiating features do not stop there.  Some of the best features
of A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; come right out of the wish list of engineers implementing messaging
driven solutions.  These&amp;nbsp;include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wildcard destinations (instead of having to implement non-interrupting
  listeners with their own logic to determine if a message is of interest
  or using overly generic destination&amp;nbsp;names)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Composite destinations (instead of having to implement multiple listeners
  with identical&amp;nbsp;implementations)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exclusive consumers (instead of having to implement logical or physical
  architecture to affect the sticky nature of a message&amp;nbsp;recipient)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Message groups (instead of having to implement both logical and physical
  architecture to manage message load and exclusivity&amp;nbsp;simultaneously)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any deployment strategy, A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; operates as a message broker, offering logic
and functionality to accept messages from a variety of protocols in a variety
of technologies and apply the necessary steps to reliably store and/or transmit
those messages to a suitable destination.  However, the architecture of an A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt;
deployment is not limited to single-point; brokers can be networked together
for the benefit of high availability, firewall traversal, store &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; forward
function, and a global messaging namespace.  Particularly in corporate
networks messaging to or from satellite locations, the ability to traverse
firewalls and create a bi-directional connection to a known source or
destination is a powerful&amp;nbsp;feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Demo&amp;nbsp;Time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As A-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; absorbs features from Apache ActiveMQ, Hiram walked us through a major
upcoming feature: LevelDB support.  Level &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt;, and replicated Level &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt; support,
stands to increase the base level of stored message performance by more than
100% over Kaha &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt; - the current default message&amp;nbsp;store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Hiram used Zookeeper, Active &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MQ&lt;/span&gt; and Level &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DB&lt;/span&gt; to demonstrate message
replication, high availability broker configuration and both producer and
consumer recovery scenarios when those processes experienced unexpected
termination&amp;nbsp;events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Join&amp;nbsp;Us&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shadow-Soft is proud to continue hosting knowledge rich sessions in the Atlanta
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JBUG&lt;/span&gt; meetup.  We hope you will spend an evening with us for some knowledge
sharing, personal networking and enlightening perspectives on Open Source
developments in the JBoss&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="RedHat"></category><category term="A-MQ"></category><category term="JBoss"></category><category term="Open Source"></category><category term="Apache"></category><category term="Active MQ"></category></entry></feed>