<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Just a blog.</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/thoughts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2013-08-20T14:37:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>The Importance of Choosing Open Source</title><link href="/posts/2013/Aug/20/the-importance-of-choosing-open-source" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-08-20T14:37:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Matt Dugan</name></author><id>tag:,2013-08-20:posts/2013/Aug/20/the-importance-of-choosing-open-source</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Business requires software.  But, not all software is created equal.  Some
software vendors would have you write a check based on marketing materials and
documentation alone.  Sure, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;POC&lt;/span&gt; might have worked but how do you really know
what you are getting into?  Would you buy a car with the hood welded shut, even
if you never planned to do your own maintenance?  Open Source software, and the
vendors which fully embrace the Open Source model, have nothing to hide and
your business has everything to&amp;nbsp;gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Shadow-Soft and Open&amp;nbsp;Source&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Shadow-Soft, we fully embrace the Open Source development model.  We believe
it to be the superior way to develop quality software, and the solutions we sell
every day are composed of Open Source&amp;nbsp;software.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linus Torvalds, originator of the Linux kernel, famously said &amp;#8220;With enough
eyeballs, all bugs are shallow.&amp;#8221;  Now, to a customer buying software, less bugs
is obviously better.  But, how do you make a direct comparison?  With
proprietary software, you cannot see the bug list, it&amp;#8217;s hidden.  To make a
direct comparison, compare the mean time to resolution of a found bug.  Our
customers compare the time it takes the upstream Open Source project to resolve
a defect with the time it takes their proprietary software vendor to resolve a
defect (vs just respond - watch out when your vendor &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SLA&lt;/span&gt; just identifies a
response and not a resolution).  Many times, patches are available in Open
Source upstream within hours &amp;#8212; and they are available to&amp;nbsp;everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Open Source, that means free&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, Open Source doesn&amp;#8217;t mean free of cost though many
times the two do go hand in hand.  Open Source is a development model, it means
that the code that makes up the piece of software is developed out in the open.
Anyone can view the code, download the code, compile the code themselves, etc.
Nothing is hidden and nothing is secret.  While a corporation may practice
closed development and sale of proprietary software, they often prefer to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;
Open Source software because they know it has been vetted and they gain the
ability to inspect the code if they believe a problem is occurring.  Paying for
Open Source typically provides for support, back ported defect fixes into the
version you pay for (versus the bleeding edge of development) and architectural&amp;nbsp;assurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;But why shouldn&amp;#8217;t I buy proprietary&amp;nbsp;software?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to think about this question is to consider the development
department of any company you or a friend has worked for any period of&amp;nbsp;time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Were releases of the software bug&amp;nbsp;free?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was the focus to complete and ship or take however long it took for top&amp;nbsp;quality?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Were any major bugs ever found just before a release?  How were they&amp;nbsp;resolved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many people were on the development team?  Were they equally good?  Were they equally&amp;nbsp;passionate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking in these lines, it is easy to see how &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; software could be shipped
with quick fixes, brittle underpinnings, inadequate quality enforcement, etc.
The difference is in how it is sold.  Proprietary software is sold as if it is
crafted by a team of geniuses who cause permanent and stable solutions to appear
into reality by pure force of will and determination.  Can you think of any
development department exhibiting those characteristics?  If you can, consider
if the characteristics are common or&amp;nbsp;uncommon?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Source development is about recognizing the temptation to mask imperfection
and instead put forth your best efforts as if the whole world is watching -
because on any given day, it really could.  Open Source is a meritocracy where
developers are known for their works and anyone, including your business, can
chip in, customize, and leverage the work and passions of&amp;nbsp;many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Decision point - buy Open Source and leverage your Open Source&amp;nbsp;vendor.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you choose Open Source software for your business you are making an
balanced investment.  You are investing in the community of developers by adding
your own energy to finding defects and contributing enhancements and
customizations.  You are investing in your vendor by contributing funds to
enhance the quality of the software according to your real usage of it - so the
software improves in its ability to meet the needs of your organization over
time.  Finally, you are investing in yourself.  By bringing Open Source software
to your business, you are enabling your team to inspect and integrate custom
solutions at the deepest levels of the software while still being able to take
advantage of contributed solutions and knowledge brought into the Open Source&amp;nbsp;community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Want to know&amp;nbsp;more?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shadow-Soft is sponsoring this year&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.allthingsopen.org/"&gt;All Things
Open&lt;/a&gt; conference this year in Raleigh, North
Carolina.  I&amp;#8217;ll be giving a talk about Open Source in your business along with
other top tier Open Source industry representatives.  If Open Source
development, business or culture interests you, please do come out and visit us
at our booth and come meet me and my fellow Shadow-Soft&amp;nbsp;colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="RedHat"></category><category term="Cloud"></category><category term="Open Source"></category><category term="Business"></category></entry></feed>